Guide to the Darlene Clark Hine Papers, circa 1879-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1996 RL.00546
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research and Writings Series, circa 1879-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1996, 14 boxes
  Arranged into two subseries, Major Writings and Other Writings and Projects. Contains drafts, correspondence, reviews, and supporting research materials for Hine's major publications: Black Victory: The Rise and Fall of the White Primary in Texas (1979); When the Truth is Told: a History of Black Women's Culture and Community in Indiana (1981); Black Women in White: Racial Conflict and Cooperation in the Nursing Profession, 1890-1950 (1989); More Than Chattel: Black Women and Slavery in the Americas (1995); and a historical research project, Black Women in the Middle West, which led to the creation of an archives on the topic at the Indiana Historical Society, and to a journal article in Signs on black women and rape in the Midwest. Early dates represent reproductions of archival materials, chiefly photographs for Hines' work on African American nurses in the U.S. There is also material in the Major Writings Subseries on Hines' work on the Blacks in the Diaspora Series, published by Indiana University Press. The Other Writings and Projects Subseries houses similar documentation for writings appearing in journals, encyclopedias, and works edited by Hine. Most notable is the material on Eyes on the Prize, History of the Civil Rights Era Reader, for which Hine contributed two chapters; these two boxes contain many folders of interviews, including correspondence and interviews both conducted by and with Fred D. Gray, prominent civil rights era attorney who represented both Rosa Parks and Martin Luther King, Jr. during the sixties. Finally, the Other Writings and Projects Subseries contains documentation on Hines' numerous media projects on black women and African American history. Files are either arranged chronologically or alphabetically by folder title.
  - Major Writings Subseries, circa 1879-1996 and undated, 6 boxes
    Groups for major works are arranged in chronological order; files within are usually grouped alphabetically by title.
    - Black Victory: The Rise and Fall of the White Primary in Texas (1979), 1975-1980, and undated
      - Correspondence, 1975 Jan.-1980 Jan., 31 folders (Box 28)
      - Revised dissertation, 1977 (Box 28)
      - Comments, undated (Box 28)
      - Interview with Roy Wilkins, undated (Box 28)
    - When the Truth is Told: a History of Black Women's Culture and Community in Indiana (1981), 1981-1982, and undated
      - Book reviews, 1982 Mar-1982 June (Box 28)
      - Correspondence, 1981 Sept. (Box 28)
      - Manuscript, 1981 (Box 28)
      - Neswletters, 1981 May (Box 28)
      - Speeches, 1981 June (Box 28)
      - Draft, undated (Box 29)
      - Photo negative, undated (Box 29)
    - Black Women in White: Racial Conflict and Cooperation in the Nursing Profession, 1890-1950 (1989), circa 1879-1993 and undated
      - Book reviews, 1991-1993, 9 folders (Box 29)
      - Brochures, 1990 (Box 29)
      - Correspondence, 1982 Jan.-1990 Dec., 19 folders (Box 29)
      - Agreements, undated (Box 29)
      - Photographs from archives, circa 1879-1960s (reproductions), 3 folders (Box 29)
      - Paperback copy of Black Women in White, undated (Box 29)
    - Black Women in the Middle West Project, 1963-1985 (Box 30)
      - Clippings, 1963-1987, 4 folders (Box 30)
      - Collector's manual, 1984 May (Box 30)
      - Conference, 1983 Mar.- 1985 Oct., 5 folders (Box 30)
      - Correspondence, 1982 Mar.-1989 Aug., 30 folders (Box 30)
      - Essays, 1982 Nov. (Box 30)
      - Participant list, 1984 Jan.-1985 June, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - Progress reports, 1984 Mar.-1985 July, 5 folders (Box 30)
      - Proposal, 1982-1983 Mar., 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Newsletters, 1982 Oct. (Box 31)
      - News releases, 1984 Feb.-1984 Nov. and undated, 5 folders (Box 31)
      - Forms, undated (Box 31)
      - Notes, undated (Box 31)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 31)
    - More Than Chattel: Black Women and Slavery in the Americas, (1995), 1988-1996
      - Correspondence, 1987 Nov.-1996 Apr., 31 folders (Box 31)
    - Blacks in the Diaspora Series
      - Correspondence, 1984 June-1992 July (Box 32)
      - Correspondence, 1992 Aug.-1995 Dec. (Box 33)
  - Other Writings and Projects Subseries, 1976-1993 and undated, 8 boxes
    Contains material relating to Hines' research, writing, and publication of journal articles, essays, edited works, and media projects.
    - The Black Professionals, 1976-1987, and undated (Box 34)
      - Correspondence, 1976 Mar.-1976 July, 4 folders (Box 34)
      - Legal, 1987 Nov. (Box 34)
      - Medicine, 1977 Sept.-1982 Nov. and undated, 17 folders (Box 34)
      - Drafts, undated, 3 folders (Box 34)
    - Eyes on the Prize, History of the Civil Rights Era Reader (1992), 1986-1992 (Box 35)
      - Fred D. Gray correspondence, 1986-1992, 7 folders (Box 35)
      - Interviews conducted by Fred D. Gray, 1985-1989
        - David Garrow, 1985 (Box 36)
        - Joe Azbell, 1989 (Box 36)
        - Paul Henderson, 1989 (Box 36)
        - Cathy Campbell, 1989 (Box 36)
        - Gennie Garrett, 1989 (Box 36)
      - Interviews conducted by Hine, 1985-1989 and undated
        - Nancy Gray, 1985 (Box 36)
        - Detroit Lee, 1989 (Box 36)
        - Bernice Hill Gray, 1989 (Box 36)
        - Otis Pickard, 1989 (Box 36)
        - Fred D. Gray, 1989 and undated, 6 folders (Box 36)
        - Milton McGregor, undated (Box 36)
      - Fred D. Gray manuscript draft, 1991, 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Eyes on the Prize, History of the Civil Rights Era Reader, chapter drafts, 1991, 4 folders (Box 37)
    - Journal Articles, 1976-1987
      - American Historical Review, 1984 (Box 38)
      - American Quarterly, 1982 (Box 38)
      - Black Studies in the United States, 1990 (Box 38)
      - Essence Magazine, 1984 (Box 38)
      - Feminist Studies, 1982 (Box 38)
      - Georgia Historical Quarterly, 1981 (Box 38)
      - The History Teacher, 1982-1984, 3 folders (Box 38)
      - Historical Society of Michigan, 1988 (Box 38)
      - Humanities Review, 1982 (Box 38)
      - Indiana Military Historical Journal, 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Journal of American History, 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Journal of Black Studies, 1977 (Box 38)
      - Journal of Ethnic Studies, 1985, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Journal of the History of Sexuality 1989 (Box 38)
      - Journal of the History of Medicine 1983 (Box 38)
      - Journal of Negro Education, 1982 (Box 38)
      - Journal of Negro History, 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Journal of Women's History, 1987-1992, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Muses 1991 (Box 38)
      - National Women's Association Journal, 1987 (Box 38)
      - Negro History Bulletin, 1977 Sept.-1977 Oct. (Box 38)
      - Phylon 1976 (Box 38)
      - Sage, 1985 (Box 38)
      - Signs, 1985-1992, 3 folders (Box 38)
      - Southwest Review, 1982 (Box 38)
      - Teaching History, 1980 (Box 38)
      - Texas State Historical Assciation, 1976 (Box 38)
      - Third World in Perspective, 1989 (Box 38)
      - Western Journal of Black Studies, 1984 (Box 38)
    - Contribution to Books and Encyclopedias, 1977-1993
      - 1977-1978, New Perspectives on Black Education History, 2 folders (Box 39)
      - 1981-1988, Images of Nursing in History (Box 39)
      - 1982, Women and Health in America (Box 39)
      - 1982-1985, Encyclopedia of Southern Culture, 2 folders (Box 39)
      - 1982, Black Leaders in Twentieth Century (Box 39)
      - 1985, Send Us a Lady Physician (Box 39)
      - 1986, The State of Afro-American History: Past, Present and Future (Box 39)
      - 1988-1992, The Health of Black Americans, 3 folders (Box 39)
      - 1989, Visible Women (Box 39)
      - 1989, Reader's Encyclopedia of American History (Box 39)
      - 1990-1991, U.S. History as Women's History (Box 39)
      - 1991-1992, Encyclopedia of African American Culture and History (Box 39)
      - 1991-1992, Southern Women Histories and Identities (Box 39)
      - 1992, Lure and Loathing (Box 39)
      - 1992, Let My People Go (Box 39)
      - 1993, The Encyclopedia of African American Women (Box 39)
    - Reviews, 1988-1992
      - 1985-1990, Article reviews, 5 folders (Box 40)
      - 1981-1991, Book Reviews, 21 folders (Box 40)
    - Media and Film Projects, 1984-1993
      - American Nurse Film Project, 1984 May-1987, 8 folders (Box 41)
      - Blacks in America, 1988 (Box 41)
      - A Century of Women, 1993 Aug., 3 folders (Box 41)
      - Constitution film project, 1985 Feb.-1985 Mar. (Box 41)
      - Ida B. Wells film project, 1988 May-1988 June, 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Let Them Come Alive slide project, 1985 Apr. (Box 41)
      - National Council of Negro Women: Black Women's History Project, 1985 Apr. (Box 41)
      - National African-American Museum and Cultural Center Project, 1980-1981 (Box 41)
      - Portable Women's History Museum Project, 1984 June-1984 July (Box 41)